A Guide to the Snyder Family Photograph Collection, 1850-1900
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Special Collections, James Madison University
Snyder Family Photograph Collection1850-1900
Special Collections, James Madison University
P0004
1 Half Hollinger Box (.25 linear feet)
The Snyder Family Photograph Collection, 1850-1900, is comprised of 46 images of various men, women, and children that are members or acquaintances of the Snyder family living in Augusta County, Virginia, during the nineteenth century. Also included is a piece of notepad paper that has information about the death of various Snyder family members.
The Snyder Family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Acquisition Information
The photo album was purchased at an estate sale, from the auctioneer Charley Whetzel, along with two business ledgers belonging to John Snyder on 17 September, 2011, at Mount Solon, Virginia.
Biographical Information
The Snyder family that these images pertain to lived in Augusta County, Virginia, during the nineteenth century. It is unclear which member of the Snyder family owned and compiled the photographs in the album. However, John Snyder, who was a blacksmith in Augusta County, created the ledgers that were purchased alongside the photo album. There are images of John and two of his children in this collection, which refer to him as “Uncle John.” There is also an obituary for John A. Marshall, whose children are included in the images and referred to as cousins. From the little amount of information available, it is possible to consider that the album was owned by a sister of John Snyder who married into the Marshall family, or perhaps a child of said sister; nonetheless, records validating this information are yet to be located.
The inside cover of the photo album indicates that the images were added to it around Christmas of 1888. However, there are images of John Snyder as a boy and as an adult, indicating that the photographs were collected over the span of about seventy years between 1830 and 1900. It is also possible that many of the images are reproductions of older photographs.
Scope and Content
The Snyder Family Photograph Collection, 1850-1900, which consists of .25 linear feet, is comprised of 46 images of various men, women, and children that are members or acquaintances of the Snyder family living in Augusta County, Virginia, during the nineteenth century. Also included is a piece of notepad paper that has information about the deaths of various Snyder family members. The collection is divided into two series: Photographs and Photo Album Manuscripts.
Series I, Photographs: contains 46 images that include albumen prints, collodion prints, gelatin developing-out paper, and tintypes. All of the photos are black and white or sepia in color, and most are accompanied by a matte frame or a decorative paper sleeve. The photographs are housed individually and are arranged in the original order they were found in upon removal from the photo album, unless otherwise noted in the container list below. A fair number of the images were professionally done, and, as a whole, Series I offers a glimpse into the popular fashions of men, women, and children living in Augusta County in the second half of the nineteenth century.
Series II, Photo Album Manuscripts: includes two manuscripts that were found within the album. The first is a small piece of paper that was found behind the very first image in the album, which provides initials for a family member, photographer, or otherwise whom has not been identified. The second manuscript is a piece of notepad paper that provides details of the deaths of various Snyder family members, and was originally placed behind the front inside cover of the album.
Arrangement
Note: The call number of each photograph is “collection number—box number—photograph number.”
The arrangement of series is as follows:
I: Photographs
II: Photo Album Manuscripts
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
See also the Snyder Ledgers Collection, SC #5026.
Separated Material
The photo album and the obituaries attached to the inside covers have been discarded. However, images of both can be viewed upon special request.
Contents List
- Photographs, 1850-1900
  - P0004.01.001, c.1885-1900, Black and white, full-body front view portrait of a man and a woman; the man sits in a chair with the woman standing just behind his right shoulder. Most likely a collodion print attached to white cardboard with a gilded edge (6.25x4.25).
    Lively, East Main Street, McMinnville, Tennessee
  - P0004.01.001a, c.1885-1900, A piece of paper housed behind P0004.01.001 in the photo album. “J O, G A E” written in pencil. (6.75x4.5).
    *Housed in "Series II: Photo album Manuscripts" folder"*
  - P0004.01.002, March 5, 1892, An albumen print of a full-body front view portrait of a man and a woman posing in front of a rustic backdrop. The man sits with the woman standing by his right shoulder. Photo album caption identifies man to be “Luis Snyder.” Print is attached to cream colored cardboard with a gilded edge. (6.25x4.25).
    J.M. Hill, Bridgewater, Virginia.
  - P0004.01.003, c.1885-1900, Black and white, full body front view of two young, finely dressed children playing in a dirt road; a young boy pulls a toddler in a small wagon. Most likely a collodion print attached to cream colored cardboard (6.25x4.25).
  - P0004.01.004, c.1855-1900, Black and white, almost full body front view portrait of a young man sitting in a chair and resting his arm on a table. Photo album caption identifies man to be “Uncle John.” Tintype housed in a white paper sleeve with an ornate red border. (4x2.5).
  - P0004.01.005, c.1855-1900, Sepia, waist-up front view of a man that is looking directly into the camera. Photo album caption identifies him to be “Uncle Frank.” Most likely an albumen print attached to thin cream-colored cardboard (4x2.5).
  - P0004.01.006, c.1855-1900, Black and white, front view portrait of a young boy who is looking into the camera. A red bowtie seems to be colored/drawn in to the photo. “Luis Snyder” written in pencil on the back of the encasing, and a photo album caption also reads “Mother’s half brothers.” Tintype housed in a tan paper sleeve with an ornate red border, and a piece of lined notebook paper glued to the back (4x2.5).
  - P0004.01.007, c.1855-1900, Black and white, front view portrait of a man who is looking into the camera. Photo album caption underneath read “Mother’s half brothers.” Tintype housed in an embellished white paper sleeve (4x2.5).
  - P0004.01.008, c.1855-1900, Black and white, front view portrait of a man and a woman, who is holding an open book. This image was also housed above the photo album caption “Mother’s half brothers.” Most likely an albumen print attached to thin cream-colored cardboard (4x2.5).
    T. L. Darnell, Cumberland, Maryland.
  - P0004.01.009, c.1885-1900, Black and white, shoulders-up front view portrait of two young women. “Rena” written in pencil on the back. Most likely a collodion print attached to thick black cardboard (4.5x6).
  - P0004.01.010, c.1885-1900, Black and white, front view of a man sitting in between two women in front of a stone brick building. Caption on the back reads “my bachelor son and two of his cousins at Lincoln farm sitting on a part of the memorial building.” Possibly printed on gelatin developing-out paper. (3.5x5).
  - P0004.01.011, c.1885-1900, Black and white, shoulders-up front view of a young woman looking to the right of the camera and wearing a very ornate hat. Most likely a collodion print attached to small piece of cardboard that is cut with a gilded edge. (3x2).
  - P0004.01.012, c.1855-1900, Black and white, shoulders-up front view of a young boy who is looking into the camera. Photo album caption identifies him as “John.” Tintype housed in an embellished cream-colored paper sleeve. (3.75x2.75).
  - P0004.01.013, c.1855-1900, Black and white, shoulders-up front view of an elderly man who is looking into the camera. Photo album caption identifies him as “Father.” Tintype housed in an embellished cream-colored paper sleeve (3.75x2.75).
  - P0004.01.014, c.1855-1900, Black and white, front view portrait of a very young girl who is shyly looking into the camera. Photo album caption identifies her as “Irena.” Tintype housed in a white paper sleeve with a red border that is badly stained. (4x2.5).
  - P0004.01.015, c.1855-1900, Black and white, front view portrait of a young boy sitting who is looking into the camera and sitting in a chair. “John” written in pencil on the front of the paper sleeve. Tintype housed in a white paper sleeve with a red border that is badly stained (4x2.5).
  - P0004.01.016, c.1855-1900, Black and white, front view portrait of a young man who is looking into the camera. “John” is written in pencil on the front of the paper sleeve. Tintype housed in an orange paper sleeve with an ornate red border (4.5x3).
  - P0004.01.017, c.1855-1900, Black and white, front view portrait of a young girl. The flowers of the bow on the front of her dress seemed to be colored in red or pink. “Irena” is written in pencil on the front of the paper sleeve. Tintype housed in a cream-colored paper sleeve with a red border (4x2.5).
  - P0004.01.018, c.1850-1900, Small card with an illustration of a bird, flowers, and small house with the inscription “With God all things are possible. Matth. 19-26.” “From Pattie Marshall” is written in pencil on the back (1.75x3).
  - P0004.01.018a, 1898(?), Black and white, full-body front view of a baby girl who is looking to the left of the camera. “Miss Ellen Vogel, aged 8 months Aug 3 1898” is written in pencil on the back. Collodion print attached to cream-colored cardboard (6.5x4.25).
    Mrs. W. D. Hughes, McMinnville, Tenn.
    *This photograph is housed in the “Oversize Photographs” folder for the purpose of efficient storage.*
  - P0004.01.019, c.1855-1900, Sepia, front view of a cow standing in a fenced-in area and looking into the camera. Possibly an albumen print attached to embellished gray cardboard (4x5).
  - P0004.01.0120, c.1855-1900, Sepia, front view portrait of a baby that is looking to the right of the camera. “Myrtle Genevieve Ekleberry 5 mo old” is written in pencil on the back. Most likely an albumen print attached to white cardboard with a gilded edge (6.5x4.25).
  - P0004.01.021, c.1855-1900, Sepia, full-body front view portrait of a man and a woman that are dressed for a special occasion such as a wedding. Albumen print attached to embellished white cardboard (6.5x4.25).
    Shellabarger, Horton, Kansas.
  - P0004.01.022, c.1885-1900, Black and white, full-body front view of a young female toddler who is looking to the left of the camera. Collodion print attached to black cardboard. (5.5x4).
  - P0004.01.023, c.1885-1900, Black and white, front view portrait of a man who is looking slightly to the left of the camera. Photo album caption identifies him as “Cousin Burnet Marshall Lill’s brother.” Collodion print attached to dark grey cardboard (7x4.5).
  - P0004.01.024, c.1885-1900, Black and white, front view portrait of a man and a woman that are sitting and looking to the right of the camera, while a very young girl stands in between them with her hands on each of their shoulders and looking into the camera. Photo album caption identifies the woman as “Lill Marshall Wilson.” Collodion print attached to dark grey cardboard (4.5x6.5).
  - P0004.01.025, c.1855-1900, Sepia, full-body front view portrait of a man sitting in a chair, with a woman standing to his left and resting her arm on his shoulder. Both are looking into the camera. Albumen print attached to pink cardboard with a gold border on the front (4x2.5).
    B. A. Blakemore’s Photo Art Gallery, Augusta Street, Staunton, Virginia.
  - P0004.01.026, c.1855-1900, Sepia, front portrait view of a man with a full beard and mustache who is looking slightly to the right of the camera. Tintype housed in a white paper sleeve with an ornate red border (4.5x2.5).
  - P0004.01.027, c.1855-1900, Sepia, full-body front view of a man sitting in a chair in front of a scenic backdrop. Tintype housed in a paper sleeve with cut corners and an ornate red border (4.5x3).
  - P0004.01.028, c.1855-1900, Black and white, front view portrait of a man who is looking slightly to the right of the camera. “Cousin Joe Snyder” written in pencil on the back of the sleeve. Tintype housed in an embellished yellow and purple paper sleeve (4x2.5).
    B. A. Blakemore’s Photograph Gallery, No. 4 North Augusta Street, Staunton, Virginia.
  - P0004.01.029, c.1855-1900, Sepia, silhouette portrait of a young woman with her hair ornately braided. Possibly an albumen print that is a copy of an older photograph, glued to a thin piece of tan cardboard (4.25x2.5).
    Johnston’s Star Gallery, Richland Center, Wis.
  - P0004.01.030, c.1855-1900, Sepia, full-body portrait of an elderly man sitting in a chair and an elderly woman, who is standing next to the man with her hand resting on his shoulder. Albumen print glued to a thin piece of tan cardboard (4x2.5).
  - P0004.01.031, c.1855-1900, Black and white, front view portrait of a young man who is looking slightly to the right of the camera. Most likely an albumen print glued to a thin piece of tan cardboard with a red border (4.5x2.5).
  - P0004.01.032, c.1855-1900, Black and white, front view portrait of a middle-aged man who is looking slightly to the right of the camera. Photo album caption identifies him as “Father.” Tintype housed in a a paper sleeve that is orange with an ornate red border on the front, and purple on the back (4x2.5).
    B. A. Blakemore’s Photographic Gallery, Augusta Street, Staunton, Virginia.
  - P0004.01.033, c.1855-1900, Black and white, front view of a woman sitting in front of an elaborate backdrop. Photo album caption identifies her as “Mother.” Tintype (3.75x2.5).
  - P0004.01.034, c.1855-1900, Sepia, front view of a man who is smiling and looking into the camera. Albumen print attached to peach-colored cardboard (4x2.5).
    Locke, Richland Center, Wisconsin.
  - P0004.01.035, February 20, 1882, Black and white, front view of a young woman who is sitting and looking into the camera. Photo album caption identifies her as “Sister,” and the date is written in pencil on the back. Tintype housed in a white paper sleeve with an ornate gold border (3.75x2.5).
  - P0004.01.036, c.1855-1900, Black and white, front view of a boy who is looking into the camera. Photo album caption identifies him as “John.” Tintype housed in a tan-grey colored paper sleeve with a pink back, and an ornate gold border (4x2.5).
  - P0004.01.037, c.1855-1900, Black and white, front view of a young man looking slightly to the left of the camera. Tintype housed in an embellished light pink paper sleeve (6.25x4.25).
  - P0004.01.038, c.1885-1900, Black and white, front view of a woman who is looking to the right of the camera. Most likely a collodion print attached to green, cream, and gold cardboard (4x2.5).
    W. J. Hillman, Richland Center, Wisconsin.
  - P0004.01.039, c.1855-1900, Black and white, front view portrait of a man who is looking to the right of the camera. Tintype housed in an orange paper sleeve with an ornate red border (3.75x2.25).
  - P0004.01.040, c.1885-1900, Black and white, full-body front view portrait of a man and a woman who are looking into the camera; the man sits in a chair while the woman stands to his left, with her hand on his shoulder. They both stand in front of an elaborate backdrop. “Miss E. I. Snyder” written in blue ink on the back.Most likely a collodion print attached to green and gold cardboard (4x2.5).
  - P0004.01.041, c.1855-1900, Black and white, front view portrait of a young man who is sitting and looking to the right of the camera. Photo album caption identifies him as “Lewis Snyder.” Tintype housed in a white paper sleeve with an ornate red border (3.75x2.5).
    B. A. Blakemore’s Photograph Gallery, Staunton, Virginia.
  - P0004.01.042, c.1855-1900, Black and white, full-body front view portrait of a young woman who is sitting in a chair beside a table with a few books, which her left arm is resting on. She is posing in front of a scenic backdrop. Photo album caption identifies her as “Irena.” Tintype (3.5x2.25).
  - P0004.01.043, c.1855-1900, Black and white, full-body front view portrait of a man sitting in a chair in front of a scenic backdrop and looking into the camera. Photo album caption identifies him as “Cousin Martin Snyder.” Tintype (3.5x2).
  - P0004.01.044, c.1885-1900, Black and white, full-body portrait of a woman standing next to and resting her left hand on a chair. Most likely a collodion print attached to a piece of stained cardboard with a gold border (3.75x2.25).
  - P0004.01.045, c.1885-1900, Black and white, full-body portrait of a woman sitting on a bench with a young girl standing to her right and a young boy standing to her left. All three are posed in front of a scenic backdrop. “Belongs to Abr. & T. Paschal” written in pencil on the back. Most likely a collodion print attached to stained white cardboard with gold trim at the bottom (4x2.25).
  - P0004.01.046, c.1885-1900, Black and white, front view portrait of a man who is looking to the left of the camera. Most likely a collodion print attached to green cardboard with a gold border (4x2.5).
  - P0004.01.047, After 1901, A piece of notepad paper that was placed behind the front cover of the photo album. Contains information about the deaths of various Snyder family members (9x5.5).
    *Housed in "Series II: Photo Album Manuscripts" folder.*